So today's דף Daf is נז Nun-Zayin and we pick up three
lines from the top. I just want to say one second because
I mistranslated or interpreted the last line. The גמרא, Gemara, the משנה
Mishnah mentions all the things that are excluded from אונאה Ona'ah and
from שמירה, Shemirah, etc. and the one focused on yesterday was the
issue about קרקע, Karka, about land. And it had a question about
seeds planted in land. Are those considered to be land for these
הלכות halachos about אונאה, Ona'ah, for הלכות halachos about שבועה? Shvua? And
it had it framed in a way where it wasn't really about
the seeds per se; it was about the way the גמרא Gemara
framed it as had the land been seeded properly, so then it's
an interesting question. Is it about seeds or land? Would there be
a שבועה, Shvua, would there be אונאה? Ona'ah? But the last case
the גמרא Gemara had was a case about חדש Chadash and about
whether the עומר Omer would make it permissible. So I mistranslated that
yesterday, misinterpreted. The actual scenario is the following: the actual case is
you cut the harvest before the second day of פסח. Pesach. You
have this grain here. If you just keep it around in your
cabinet, in your jars, then when the second day of פסח Pesach
comes the grain will be permissible. But instead, what you did was
you put it in the land but it hasn't taken root. And
now the question is when the second day of פסח Pesach rolls
around, is it considered to be just like grain in a jar
and now the עומר Omer makes it permissible, or has it now
become, because it's there in the land waiting to take root, so
you no longer treat it as like grain, you treat it as
part of the land? And if you treat it as part of
the land, then there's no concept of the עומר Omer relating to
it and the עומר Omer making it permissible if you wanted to
now scoop it out of the land and eat it. So that
was the question, not what grows afterwards. What grows afterwards obviously is
not going to be permissible until it's taken root, but that it
has yet to have had the עומר Omer make it permissible, it's
in the ground, the עומר Omer comes, can you scoop it out
of the ground right now and eat it? So that was just
the case yesterday. But let's move on now, three lines from the
top. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, three lines from the top on נז
Nun-Zayin עמוד א, Amud Aleph, אמר רבא Amar Rava אמר רב חסא,
Amar Rav Chasa, אמר רב חסא, Amar Rav Chasa, interesting name, lettuce,
okay. בעי רבי אמי, Bai Rabi Ami, רבי אמי Rabi Ami asked:
אונאה אין להם, Ona'ah ein lahem, these things in the משנה, Mishnah,
land,
slaves, שטרות, Shtarot, הקדש, Hekdesh, what's the story? We know that there's
no אונאה. Ona'ah. ביטול מקח יש להם או אין להם? Bitul Mekach
yesh lahem o ein lahem? Is there an idea though that if
it's not just a sixth overcharged
but grossly overcharged or let's just say more than a sixth, with
that magic number of a sixth? Once you go more than a
sixth, we normally say the sale is בטל. batel. It's like the
sale is voided; it was such an overcharge. So that's maybe, the
גמרא Gemara says, maybe not a הלכה halacha of
אונאה, Ona'ah, because where do we know this idea that the sale
is void? I mean, somebody asked me the other day, where do
the rabbis get this idea of a sixth? It's not in the
תורה. Torah. The תורה Torah just says don't overcharge, so obviously to
some degree the rabbis used their own judgment to determine what constitutes
the overcharging of the תורה, Torah, like a concept of לא מסרה
כתוב אלא לחכמים. lo masra katuv ela lachachamim. But the question becomes
that they also assumed that at a certain amount the money was
so disproportionate to the value that it was like a voided sale.
We actually pointed out at the time the irony. The irony is
that if you're the seller and you more overcharge, you actually have
more options than if you less
overcharge, because then you can void it as well, not just the
other side. So once that's true, maybe it's conceptually a completely different
category. So even if the תורה Torah says the technical laws of
אונאה Ona'ah don't apply, certainly for example if I say I'm selling
you two acres and I only sold you one acre, then it's
a ביטול מקח. Bitul Mekach. Certainly the laws of ביטול מקח Bitul
Mekach apply if I sell you the wrong thing, if it's land
or שטרות Shtarot or slaves. So maybe a gross overcharging is just
completely like false pretenses, it's like a completely voided sale and has
nothing to do with
the laws of overcharging, which are in much more of a moderate
amount. So that's the question. Now of course the difference between a
sixth and a little bit more than a sixth is not
huge, so a logical thing might be to say well, to consider
it to be a fifth, ביטול מקח, Bitul Mekach, that's still within
the special הלכות halachos of אונאה. Ona'ah. But maybe if you charge
like twice as much, you don't need the הלכות halachos of אונאה
Ona'ah to say it's a ביטול מקח. Bitul Mekach. That objective, that
objectively is ביטול מקח. Bitul Mekach. So that is actually how תוספות
Tosafot re-reads the גמרא. Gemara. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, let's
look at a quick תוספות Tosafot even before we get into the
גמרא. Gemara. The תוספות Tosafot says the following: אמר רב נחמן הדר
אמר רב חסא אונאה אין להם ביטול מקח יש להם. Amar Rav
Nachman hadar Amar Rav Chasa Ona'ah ein lahem Bitul Mekach yesh lahem.
I didn't read the next line, so let's first read the next
line of the גמרא. Gemara. So the question is: is it ביטול
מקח Bitul Mekach or not? So the גמרא Gemara says that was
the question that רב חסא Rav Chasa asked in the name of
רבי אמי, Rabi Ami, או אין
להם. o ein lahem. אמר רב נחמן הדר אמר רב חסא, Amar
Rav Nachman hadar Amar Rav Chasa, then רב חסא Rav Chasa said
after he raised the question, פשיט רבי אמי, Pashit Rabi Ami, רבי
אמי Rabi Ami actually concluded אונאה אין להם ביטול מקח יש להם.
Ona'ah ein lahem Bitul Mekach yesh lahem. No, there actually is ביטול
מקח. Bitul Mekach. So just the special הלכות halachos of אונאה Ona'ah
of overcharging, giving back the overcharge, or allowing the cheated party to
demand a ביטול מקח, Bitul Mekach, but if it's really disproportionate, then
that has nothing to do with the special laws of אונאה, Ona'ah,
that's just ביטול מקח, Bitul Mekach, that's just a voided sale. Okay,
but now תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says, as we look at תוספות Tosafot
*Tosfos*, משמע דרב נחמן לא פליג ארב חסדא ורב פפא *mashma de-Rav
Nachman lo palig a-Rav Chisda ve-Rav Pappa*. It sounds like Rav Nachman
agrees and says that there's a הלכה halacha *halacha* of ביטול מקח
bitul mekach *bitul mekach* by things like קרקע karka, *karka*. He says,
וקשיא לרבינו תם *ve-kashya le-Rabbeinu Tam*, דבפרק המקבל *de-ve-perek ha-mekabbel* later in
בבא מציעא *Bava Metzia*, אמינא זבין בריש ושוי במאה *amina zavin be-reish
ve-shavei be-me'ah*, if you sold for 200 and it's worth 100, צר
מר מיניה *tzar mar minei*, and ואמר רב נחמן אין אונאה ona'ah
לקרקעות *ve-amar Rav Nachman ein ona'ah le-karka'os*. And Rav Nachman actually said,
no, that's actually okay, it's קרקע Karka *karka*, so even if you
charge 200 for 100, it's not a ביטול מקח bitul mekach. *bitul
mekach*. So what do you do with the fact that here he's
saying in the name of his רבי *Rebbi* that there is ביטול
מקח bitul mekach. *bitul mekach* by קרקע karka, *karka*? אלמא אפילו ביטול
מקח bitul mekach. אין להם *alma afilu bitul mekach ein lahem*. So
that's a pretty good קשיא *kashya*. ותירץ רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam *ve-teireitz
Rabbeinu Tam* דאין אונאה ona'ah עד פלגא *de-ein ona'ah ad palga*, אבל
מפלגא ואילך נקרא ביטול מקח bitul mekach, ויש להם *aval mi-palga va-eilech
nikra bitul mekach ve-yesh lahem*. No, when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אין אונאה ona'ah, *ein ona'ah*, it doesn't just mean a sixth. When
it says that they don't have אונאה hona'ah *ona'ah*, it means any
overcharging up to and including double their value. So if it's worth
100 up to charging 200 for it, where
do you get that it means double as opposed to 50%? פלגא
*palga*?
Because the example he gave is זבין בריש ושוי במאה *zavin be-reish
ve-shavei be-me'ah*. Okay, so anyway, so therefore, so that would be considered
to be within the laws of אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah*. And the special
laws of the תורה Torah *Torah* of אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah* don't apply.
But more than twice the value, more than 100% increase in its
value, that is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* means when it says
ביטול מקח יש להם Bitul mekach yesh lahem. *bitul mekach yesh lahem*.
Okay, so it's obviously not פשט pshat *pshat* of the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, because פשט *pshat* of the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is the concept
of ביטול מקח bitul mekach, *bitul mekach* applies as soon as it's
a little bit more than a sixth. All right, but nevertheless, you
understand, besides that רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* has to fit it in
with the other סוגיא *sugya*, you understand what's motivating רבינו תם *Rabbeinu
Tam*. Like to say that a fifth doesn't is all of a
sudden so disproportionate, a sixth is just אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah*, a fifth,
that's already ביטול מקח Bitul Mekach. *bitul mekach* that would apply to
קרקע *karka*, it's like you don't really see how radical of a
why that would be considered so disproportionate that it would now be
considered like objectively ביטול מקח bitul mekach, *bitul mekach*, even though something
was not in the תורה *Torah*'s category of אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah*. Something
like double the price, that already you could see. All right, so
anyway, but that's what our גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is discussing. So back
to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, you know,
that yes, the laws of אונאה ona'ah. *ona'ah* don't apply to these
things, but the laws of ביטול מקח bitul mekach *bitul mekach* do.
And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. רב יונה אמר הקדשות, Hekdeshot,
ורבי ירמיה אמר קרקעות *Rav Yona amar hekdeshos ve-Rabbi Yirmiyah amar karka'os*.
So that was in the name of רב נחמן
*Rav Nachman* in the name of רב חסדא Rav Chisda. *Rav Chisda*,
in the name of רב אמי *Rav Ami*. Now we're going to
have some statements in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan: *Rabbi
Yochanan* also about this question about whether these things are excluded just
from אונאה ona'ah. *ona'ah* or even from ביטול מקח bitul mekach *bitul
mekach*. So רב יונה *Rav Yona* was said the following statement about
הקדשות Hekdeshot, *hekdeshos*, and רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya, *Rabbi Yirmiyah* said the
following statement about land. ותרוייהו משמיה דרבי יוחנן *ve-tarvaihu mishmei de-Rabbi Yochanan*,
and both of them taught this in the name of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*. What was the statement? אמרו *amru*, they said,
אונאה אין להם ein lahem ona'ah. ביטול מקח יש להם bittul mekach
yesh lahem. *ona'ah ein lahem bitul mekach yesh lahem*. The same thing
we said before: although the laws of אונאה ona'ah *ona'ah* don't apply,
the laws of ביטול מקח bitul mekach. *bitul mekach* do. Again, פשט
*pshat* of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* would be as soon as it's
a little bit more overcharged than a sixth, the laws of ביטול
מקח bitul mekach *bitul mekach* do. According to תוספות Tosfos *Tosfos*, only
when it's a full 100% overcharge. Okay, but anyway, ביטול מקח bitul
mekach. *bitul mekach* applies to it. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants
to understand, wait, do you
know cases of הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* trying to buy land for its
purposes and you overcharge הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh*?
Like what? Yeah, yeah, or you sell land or we haven't really
worked out the הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* issue yet, but you're פודה podeh
*podeh* stuff with הקדש Hekdesh, *hekdesh*, we'll see about הקדש Hekdesh? *hekdesh*
in a minute, buying or selling or being פודה *podeh* from הקדש
Hekdesh *hekdesh*. Okay, so that if it was too different, too much
of an overcharge or an undercharge, it would be a ביטול מקח
bitul mekach, *bitul mekach*. Now the fact that one of them said
about land and one said about הקדשות *hekdeshos*, right? 'Cause the list
in the משנה mishna *Mishnah* included two separate things, right? One was
and they really are two very distinct categories. One were just certain
types of objects, right? קרקע, עבדים, avadim, שטרות shtarot, *karka, avadim, shetaros*.
And the other was not a type of an object but a
status of an object, it's הקדש Hekdesh's *hekdesh*. Or even understood more
properly because of learning this from the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* of אחיו
או רעהו *achiv o rei'ehu*, the other party that you're doing business
with. Doing business with הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* as opposed to doing business
with a הדיוט hedyot, *hedyot*. Okay, and conceptually there might be differences
in terms of those two types of cases. So here, this law
that there is ביטול מקח bitul mekach, *bitul mekach*, one said this
about land and the other said it about הקדש Hekdesh, *hekdesh*. Are
they really saying the same thing and just choosing one different thing
of the list? Or would they actually disagree about some of this
issue? So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now looks at. מאן
דאמר הקדשות *man de-amar hekdeshos*, if you say that הקדשות *hekdeshos* there's
ביטול מקח bitul mekach *bitul mekach*, כל שכן אקרקעות *kol sheken a-karka'os*,
certainly by קרקע *karka* there would be, certainly by the other half
of the list. אבל מאן דאמר קרקעות *aval man de-amar karka'os*, but
if you say just if your statement was by קרקע *karka* there's
ביטול מקח bitul mekach *bitul mekach*, אבל הקדשות *aval hekdeshos* when it
comes to הקדשות *hekdeshos*, לא *lo*, there would not be ביטול מקח
bitul mekach *bitul mekach*. Why not?
כדישמואל *ki-de-Shmuel*, because there's a reason by הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* to say
that even if it's disproportionate, it's still going to work and it
won't be ביטול מקח bitul mekach, *bitul mekach*. What reason do we
have to say that? שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*'s teaching. דאמר שמואל Shmuel *de-amar
Shmuel*, הקדש Hekdesh. שוה מנה שחיללו על שוה פרוטה pruta. מחולל *hekdesh
shaveh maneh she-chillalo al shaveh perutah mechullal*, that even if you take
הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* worth a thousand dollars, a hundred or whatever, you
know, and you transfer it to a penny, it's going to work.
So even though obviously that's completely disproportionate, you should say ביטול מקח
bitul mekach. *bitul mekach*, nevertheless it works. So if
even if you say there's ביטול מקח bitul mekach, *bitul mekach*... But
if you say this ביטול מקח bitul mekach by קרקע, הקדש Hekdesh
might be a special case. Now, I will let me say why
הקדש Hekdesh. is a special case. All we've done is we've shown
that שמואל Shmuel says so. שמואל Shmuel says you can do, you
know, a thousand dollars on a penny and it works, but we
haven't explained why. So רש"י Rashi actually explains that the reason is
because nobody can cheat הקדש Hekdesh in a funny way. Like God
knows, you know, God is all-knowing, right? So therefore if I overcharged
you by land, there's more of a, you know, anything, land, slaves
or whatever, there's more of a reason to say ביטול מקח bitul
mekach because there's more of a reason to say you would not
have agreed to it had you known that it had been so
overcharged, and therefore you were deceived and you were tricked, and therefore,
you know, therefore there was not a meeting of minds, and therefore
it's a ביטול מקח. bitul mekach? Okay, whereas by הקדש, Hekdesh. you
know, God is aware of what you're doing. Now, of course, God
is not going to step in, yeah, but okay, but certainly well,
you know, it's an interesting question, right? Because what's the scenario by
הקדש? Hekdesh. And I'm going to get to that number two. Are
you talking about פדיון pidyon or are you talking about a type
of a purchase? So I'll get to that in a minute. But
so since God is like aware of what you're doing, you're not
tricking any other side. So since you're not tricking any other side,
of course you could say God would object, we don't know what
God is thinking about it, but since there's no other side to
deceive or to trick, there's not the same idea of ביטול מקח.
bitul mekach That's like what רש"י Rashi says, okay? So that's רש"י's
Rashi's understanding. I would have said it a little bit differently because
especially in the case that שמואל Shmuel is discussing. You see, this
gets to the issue of whether you think about הקדש Hekdesh as
a status or as a like ownership entity, like as a person.
If you think about it as a status, this thing has קדושה
kedusha in it. I sanctified my car to the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. Now, on the one hand, they own it. They're just an
entity, you know, like the Vatican is like one of the biggest,
להבדיל, lehavdil, like one
of the biggest, you know, property owners in Europe, right? So they
own it. They own it. Okay, they own it. That's thinking about
it as normal, they just happen to be the owner, it happens
to be the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is the owner. Then it
doesn't really conceptually, it's not so different, as Michael said also, from
רש"י's Rashi's perspective. I could trick the גזבר, gizbar, right? If the
גזבר gizbar is the one that's in charge of handling הקדש's Hekdesh,
bank account, right? So, you know, there is that thing. But if
you don't think about it that way, if you think about it
more as a status, this car that I was donated to the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, don't think of it that it's owned by,
it's in their bank account as part of their assets. Think about
it that this car is instilled with קדושה, kedusha, right? It has
this holiness in it. You know, if I misuse it or whatever,
I'll do מעילה me'ilah or something, right? So if it's filled with
this status, this קדושה, kedusha, then I can withdraw that status as
long as I have some address for it, as long as I
put it now on a penny, on a פרוטה. pruta, Okay, I'm
not actually buying it off of הקדש Hekdesh. for a פרוטה, pruta.
I'm transferring the status to a פרוטה. pruta, Okay, that's why it
works. So that's why שמואל Shmuel could say, now, it could be
both are true. You know, שמואל Shmuel could say בדיעבד bedi'eved it
works if you did that, because that you focused on it as
קדושה kedusha and you transferred קדושה. kedusha. לכתחילה lechatchila you're not allowed
to do that because essentially from the ownership aspect, you're cheating הקדש,
Hekdesh, right? You are actually taking something worth ten thousand dollars and
only giving הקדש Hekdesh, a penny.
So what if he paid nine thousand?
Well, we'll talk about that, okay? But the point is is that
anyway, this transfer maybe we should say ביטול מקח. bitul mekach So
one way of explaining this is is that, you know, is that
no, it is true, but because you can also look at it
through this other lens, you could look at it a lens of
just buying and selling and there should be ביטול מקח, bitul mekach
but because you could look at it through this lens of transferring
of קדושה, kedusha, that made, right, it wasn't a מקח mekach per
se because it wasn't a מקח. mekach. Okay, you weren't doing a
מקח mekach at that stage. What you were doing was transferring קדושה
kedusha and it happened to work. Okay, so you did an end
run around the whole thing. So that's like a very different way
of thinking about it. Now, of course, the question could be then
it should depend on the circumstances. As Michael said, right, let's say
I donated my car to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and comes
along the גזבר, gizbar, Michael is the גזבר, gizbar, and he picked
it up, right? It's cars for kids, it's cars for הקדש. Hekdesh,
Okay, so now what's הקדש Hekdesh going to do with my 97
Camry? So it's cars for
כהונה. kehuna. Right, cars for כהונה. kehuna. So now Michael goes around
and he turns it over there, he sells it to Jenna for
a thousand dollars, okay? Thing is, or for ten thousand dollars, thing
is it was, well, let's say a thousand, okay whatever, thing is
it was worth more, it was worth less. So the question is
now when Jenna pays the money, that money gets קדושה kedusha and
Jenna gets the car, okay? But that was done not as פדיון,
pidyon, that was done as a purchase, as a buying and a
selling. So maybe that case there should be ביטול מקח, bitul mekach
right? Because that case you can't reframe as a type of a
פדיון. pidyon. So just because שמואל Shmuel says if I take the
my own car that I sanctified and before the גזבר gizbar comes
to pick it up, I transfer it onto money, that works. But
if the גזבר gizbar has now picked it up and the גזבר
gizbar is selling it and taking the proceeds. Maybe that is very
different. As Michael says from רש״י's Rashi perspective, the גזבר Gizbar could
be tricked or the גזבר Gizbar could be tricking somebody else. Right,
that's also the point. Let's say הקדש Hekdesh is doing is, is
doing the overcharging, not the other direction. Okay, and that really is
much more a type of a transaction. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't
really unpack all of that, but the גמרא Gemara just says it's
possible that there's מקח טעות Mekach Ta'ut by קרקע and not by
הקדש. Hekdesh הקדש Hekdesh, is a different entity, as רש״י Rashi says
there's no side to be duped, and the way I'm saying it
you could frame it as a פדיון Pidyon not as a מקח,
Mekach, but that doesn't address cases which really much more are מקח,
Mekach, why that should be excluded from this idea of ביטול מקח.
bittul mekach Yes.
But another way to say what you're saying is that that object
can function in both ways almost simultaneously. When the גזבר Gizbar sells
it to somebody else, that's not
an act of
הקדשה, Hakdasha, that's a, well, פדיון, Pidyon, you mean.
Right, so that's the point. You would think that that thing you
would look at as a מכירה Mechira which effects the transfer of
the קדושה, Kedusha, but not fundamentally an act of transfer of קדושה.
Kedusha. And therefore that's one you would want to function more within
the ways other מכירות Mechiras function.
Yes, but somewhat we stack the cards in favor of הקדש. Hekdesh
Meaning like if they overcharge someone they can't be held liable, but
if you overcharge them like a minute, like a minute amount, they
should be, so we're going to get there.
So let's take a look, because now we're going to continue with
this discussion of הקדש. Hekdesh
Okay, תנן התם. tnan hatam. We taught over there.
אם היה קדש בעל מום יצא לחולין. im haya kodesh ba'al mum
yatza lechullin. Now this was a case in a teaching over there
about תמורה, Tmura, about trying to say this animal is in exchange
for this, and you made it a תמורה, Tmura, okay, but if
however it says that you basically the animal had a blemish and
you said it in a way, רש״י Rashi actually has the language,
you said it in a way which wasn't תמורה Tmura but which
was a way of פדיון, Pidyon, I think you said not
זו תחת זו zu tachat zu but you said
if you said זו מחוללת על זו, zu mechulelet al zu, this
should be redeemed on this, which is a language of פדיון, Pidyon,
not a language of תמורה, Tmura, not an exchange for, then if
the original animal was a בעל מום, ba'al mum, was a קרבן,
korban, when you can redeem a בעל מום, ba'al mum, so you
can redeem it on money, you could also redeem it on an
animal if you actually used the language of redemption and not the
language of exchange. So that's the teaching there, but that's not what's
going to be our interest. אם היה קדש בעל מום יצא לחולין.
im haya kodesh ba'al mum yatza lechullin. ו, Ve,
here's the question: צריך לעשות לו דמים. tzarich la'asot lo damim. You
have to figure out the accounting. Let's say animal number two was
worth, if animal number two was worth more than animal number one,
fine, you gave an extra donation to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
But if animal number two was worth less than animal number one,
you have to pay the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash the difference because
you're redeeming and you're supposed to, even though שמואל Shmuel? says you
could redeem on a פרוטה, you're supposed to redeem on the equivalent.
That's what צריך לעשות לו דמים tzarich la'asot lo damim means. Now,
what's the weight of that? אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, said
רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan יצא לחולין דבר תורה, yatza lechullin devar Torah,
תורה it works even just with any exchange no matter how much
animal number two was worth, וצריך לעשות לו דמים מדבריהם, ve'tzarich la'asot
lo damim midivreihem, and the extra difference now you have to pay
if there's a difference in value, that's only rabbinically. But biblically you
were done as soon as you did any transfer. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish אומר: omer: אף צריך לעשות לו דמים מן התורה. af tzarich
la'asot lo damim min HaTorah. No, even מן התורה min HaTorah you
have to do it. So this seems to be our debate, right?
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. seems to be like consistent with שמואל Shmuel
that it works if you did it on less, and ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish seems to be saying no, even by הקדש Hekdesh it
has to be the right amount. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this,
במאי עסקינן, bemai askinan, now
what's the case here where there's a difference between animal one and
animal two? How big of a difference? אילימא בכדי אונאה, Ilema bichdei
ona'ah,
if it's under the אונאה ona'ah, amount or equal to or under
the אונאה ona'ah, amount, one sixth or less of a difference, then
בהא לימא beha leima ריש לקיש Reish Lakish צריך לעשות לו דמים
דבר תורה? tzarich la'asot lo damim devar Torah? Would ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish in that scenario say you have to make up the difference?
Then what's the point of teaching הקדש אין לו אונאה? Hekdesh ein
lo ona'ah? Which means that up to the אונאה, ona'ah whatever, that
doesn't affect, it doesn't affect. והתנן, Vehatnan, אלו דברים שאין
להם אונאה הקרקעות והעבדים והשטרות וההקדשות. elu devarim she'ein lahem ona'ah karka'ot
ve'avadim u'shtarot ve'hekdeshot. All right, so if הקדש אין לו אונאה Hekdesh
ein lo ona'ah means anything, it means that when you do the
transaction up to and equal to a sixth, I mean less than
a sixth you would actually say would work even with a הדיוט,
okay, but up to a sixth, that's אין לו אונאה, ein lo
ona'ah, so that doesn't affect the sale, so it shouldn't affect the
transaction, so how would ריש לקיש Reish Lakish say it doesn't work
until you do an equivalent amount? Okay, that's not possible. By the
way, תוספות Tosfos says just parenthetically that let's say animal one was
worth a thousand and animal two was worth eight hundred. According to
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, before I took the extra two hundred to
הקדש, Hekdesh what happens? Is zero redeemed or is eight hundred of
it redeemed but not the remaining two hundred? So תוספות Tosfos says
part number two, eight hundred of the original animal is redeemed on
animal two and the remaining two hundred I need to add another
two hundred. Okay, but either way, thank you, if it's within a
sixth, then it's okay, it's allowed. bit off, but that's אונאה ona'ah
אין להם. So, you know, obviously ריש לקיש Resh Lakish wouldn't say
you only once you put up the balance does it work. אלא
Ella must be we're talking about,
he says, paying the חומש. chomesh.
That's a good point too, but let's not worry about that. You're
right. אלא Ella says the גמרא, Gemara but we already decided that
the חומש chomesh wasn't מעכב. me'akev. Yeah, that's a good point. Okay,
אלא ביטול מקח. Ella bitul mekach. So the difference is a difference
of ביטול מקח, bittul mekach more than a sixth. Or for רבינו
תם double, but we'll say more than a sixth. אלא ביטול מקח.
Ella bitul mekach. So now you have this ביטול מקח bittul mekach
and we have Rabbi Yochanan saying it still works even when it's
very overpriced or underpriced. בהא לימא רבי יוחנן צריך להוסיף דמים מדבריהם?
Beha leima Rabbi Yochanan tzarich lehosif damim midivreihem? Would Rabbi Yochanan say
the only need to add the difference would be rabbinic, that fundamentally
it would work? Why not? Well, it depends on whether you think
ביטול מקח bitul mekach, applies to הקדש. Hekdesh דאמר רבי יונה אהקדשות
רבי ירמיה אמר קרקעות דהא משמיה דרבי יוחנן אמרי אונאה אין להם
ביטול מקח יש להם. D'amar Rabbi Yona a-Hekdeshot Rabbi Yirmiya amar karka'ot
d'ha mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan amri ona'ah ein lahem bitul mekach yesh lahem.
At least according to רבי יונה, Rabbi Yona, meaning we're going to
bracket the other one, who was the other one here, רבי ירמיה,
but he was part of the quote. But the point here is
about רבי יונה. Rabbi Yona. רבי יונה Rabbi Yona says in the
name of Rabbi Yochanan that by הקדש, Hekdesh? there is ביטול מקח.
Mekach. So if there is ביטול מקח Mekach, by הקדש, Hekdesh. how
does it work when you go from a thousand to 800? That
should be ביטול מקח. Mekach, And if you don't want to say
ביטול מקח, there's actually an interesting תוספות Tosfos, because תוספות Tosfos says,
I don't understand, according to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, if ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish says it doesn't work because of the concept of ביטול
מקח, why do you just add the extra 200? Why don't we
just avoid the whole thing? Isn't that what ביטול מקח means? So
you could say that the point is that here we view it
as an ongoing process, you know, it doesn't work until you add
the extra money. But the other thing תוספות Tosfos says is that
the reason, it's very ingenious תוספות, Tosfos, the reason for ביטול מקח
is basically to protect the parties, right? Here you grossly overcharged me,
we're going to say ביטול מקח because, you know,
otherwise I'm going to wind up having been
cheated. You're going to go ahead and take the object and you
wait until the time that I can show to friends and I
didn't show it, because he has a question how long do I
have to do ביטול מקח, whatever, anyway I'm going to be cheated.
So therefore we have to say, you know, there's only one option:
ביטול מקח. Whereas
by הקדש, Hekdesh, תוספות Tosafot says, don't worry, הקדש Hekdesh has its
interests protected. How does it have its interests protected? Because even if
we don't say ביטול מקח, so you're not going to go ahead
and now cheat out הקדש Hekdesh because why? Because $200 of the
cow still remain unredeemed and there's still an איסור issur of מעילה
me'ilah by that cow. So הקדש Hekdesh. doesn't lose anything by, as
it were, waiving its right for ביטול מקח as long as it
says it won't be final until you do the rest of the
money, right?
Meaning you don't gain anything.
You don't gain anything, right, you don't gain anything. Right, so ביטול
מקח means, means there's some problem,
it's not final. There's something disproportionate here, it's not going to work.
But not going to work could mean to be interpreted in two
ways. It could be it's not going to work in the whole
sale is void, start again from scratch, nothing happens. Or it could
mean it's not going to work which is it's not going to
work until the difference is paid. Right,
so תוספות Tosafot basically says by הקדש, Hekdesh, הקדש Hekdesh is always
around, הקדש Hekdesh can always come and get you, הקדש Hekdesh, is
always going to, there'll always be the קדושה, kedusha, there'll always be
מעילה. me'ilah. So הקדש hekdesh, can say it's not final until you
pay the difference. But a normal person who walks away and goes
home and he goes back, you know, to his hometown after he
bought the thing, whatever, obviously there it's to protect the interests more
you have to say no, it's that the sale is void. But
the basic point for us, so that's an interesting sidebar by תוספות,
Tosafot but the basic point by us is that here we have
the idea that Rabbi Yochanan says it works. Pay the difference rabbinically
but fundamentally it works even when it's being gross- even when it's
being grossly underpaid. It's 1000 for an $800 thing. So therefore the
גמרא Gemara says how does that work according to רבי יונה Rabbi
Yona that says that by הקדש hekdesh there's ביטול מקח? So ביטול
מקח should mean that it doesn't work. Either it doesn't work at
all or it doesn't work for the remainder of it, like ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish says. But how can Rabbi Yochanan say that it
works and the only remaining difference is a rabbinic issue? Where is
that concept of ביטול מקח by הקדש? hekdesh That's the גמרא'ס Gemara's
question. I'll take your question in a second, Jim, but let's just
read the answer. So the גמרא Gemara says, בהא לימא רבי יוחנן
רבי יוחנן צריך
להוסיף דמים מדבריהם?
Beha leima Rabbi Yochanan Rabbi Yochanan
tzarich
lehosif damim midivreihem?
Oh we just read that. ביטול מקח יש להם. bittul mekach yesh
lahem.
So how could that be? If there's ביטול מקח how could it
be that fundamentally it works according to Rabbi Yochanan? So the גמרא
Gemara says, ולעולם בביטול מקח. Ve-olam be-bitul mekach.
You're right, the amount of overcharge is the ביטול מקח degree of
overcharge. So then how does it work according to Rabbi Yochanan from
רבי יונה'ס Rabbi Yona's perspective? So the גמרא Gemara. says, ואיפוך דרבי
יוחנן לריש לקיש ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן, Ve-ipech d'Rabbi Yochanan l'Resh Lakish,
Resh Lakish l'Rabbi Yochanan, reverse the positions. Okay? So Rabbi Yochanan is
the one who is saying now like ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. Lakish,
that because he holds basically ביטול מקח *bitul mekach* by הקדש hekdesh
*hekdesh*, what that translates into is that the פדיון Pidyon, *pidyon* is
not final until the extra two hundred dollars is added, okay, because
fundamentally there's a concept of ביטול מקח *bitul mekach* which means it's
not final until the 200 is added. And ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
*Reish Lakish* says, no, no ביטול מקח *bitul mekach* by הקדש hekdesh?
*hekdesh*, even if you went from 1,000 to 800, the sale is
final. All right, so same, we're just sort of reversing רב יוחנן
*Reb Yochanan*. And the גמרא *Gemara* says and here's what they argue
about, מר אית ליה דשמואל מר לית ליה דשמואל *mar is lei
de'Shmuel mar leis lei de'Shmuel*,
that it works if you go from $1,000 to a penny. מר
אית ליה דשמואל מר לית ליה דשמואל *mar is lei de'Shmuel mar
leis lei de'Shmuel*, one holds of שמואל *Shmuel* and one doesn't. Because
שמואל *Shmuel* is, it's exactly what we said before. Do you have
a concept of ביטול מקח *bitul mekach* by הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* means,
do you hold of שמואל *Shmuel*? When you do a grossly different
disproportionate transfer, if you say fundamentally it works, then what you're saying
is that there's no concept of ביטול מקח *bitul mekach* by הקדש
hekdesh, *hekdesh*. If you're saying fundamentally it doesn't work until you pay
the remainder of the value, then you're saying there is a concept
of ביטול מקח *bitul mekach* by הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*. So they're debating
שמואל *Shmuel*. So in order to get רב יוחנן *Reb Yochanan* to
be the one that says there is ביטול מקח *bitul mekach* by
הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh*, meaning to disagree with שמואל *Shmuel*, we're going to
get him to say the position that ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish
Lakish* was saying, to say that it doesn't work until you actually,
it doesn't finish working until you actually pay the difference. Yes, Jenna?
So logistics of how ביטול מקח *bitul mekach* would work with הקדש
hekdesh *hekdesh*. Once you've made it הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*, right, wouldn't there
be a problem undoing that?
Right, so that's what תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says. What we mean is
because fundamentally there's a concept of ביטול מקח *bitul mekach*, what it
means is is that the sale wasn't... it's not done when you
do a disproportionate amount. So the way it works is, right, when
you did 1,000 to 800, right, the way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* explains
it, it's 800 was transferred but the remaining 200 was not transferred.
We don't allow the disproportionate part to work. Okay. And so you
that still remains to be redeemed. All right. So that's what we're
saying now, that if רב יוחנן *Reb Yochanan* says there is ביטול
מקח *bitul mekach*, it means the remainder part cannot be redeemed unless
you have an equivalent amount, which means that he argues on שמואל
*Shmuel*. Okay. And there he says you have to supply the remainder
amount for it to finish working דאורייתא *de'oraisa*. Okay. And now the
גמרא *Gemara* has another way of understanding their debate.
How to understand רב יוחנן *Reb Yochanan* between two things, so what
about the other?
Well, the other one it doesn't bother us. The other one is
can work, you know. רב יוחנן's *Reb Yochanan's* position that says what?
רב ירמיה *Reb Yirmiyah*? No, רב ירמיה *Reb Yirmiyah* isn't the problem
because רב ירמיה *Reb Yirmiyah* says רב יוחנן *Reb Yochanan* only said
it by קרקע *karka*. By הקדש hekdesh? *hekdesh* he would say that
there's no ביטול מקח *bitul mekach*, so that works to saying it
could be disproportionate, right? Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this, אי בעית אימא *ei ba'is eima*, if you want I could
say another way of understanding the debate of רב יוחנן *Reb Yochanan*
and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish* is not a fundamental debate
of שמואל *Shmuel*. Maybe they all agree that שמואל *Shmuel* works בדיעבד
*be'di'eved*, but maybe it's a לכתחילה l'chatchilah *lechatchila* debate. אי בעית אימא
דכולי עלמא אית להו דשמואל והכא בהא קמיפלגי *ei ba'is eima de'chulei
alma it lehu de'Shmuel ve'hacha be'ha kamiflagi*. Everybody agrees to שמואל *Shmuel*.
מר סבר שחילל אין לכתחילה l'chatchilah לא *mar savar she'chilel in lechatchila
lo*. בדיעבד *be'di'eved* it works, but you're not allowed לכתחילה l'chatchilah *lechatchila*
to do it. So therefore, if you did 1,000 onto 800, it
works, but maybe there's some type of a still לכתחילה l'chatchilah דאורייתא
*lechatchila de'oraisa* to pay the remaining amount. Fundamentally, there is apparently like
no ביטול מקח *bitul mekach*, I guess, and fundamentally it works, but
you're לכתחילה l'chatchilah *lechatchila* supposed to pay the remainder amount. ומר סבר
אפילו לכתחילה *u'mar savar afilu lechatchila*. And the other says even לכתחילה
*lechatchila* you can do it disproportionate. Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* objects to
this. First of all, he just morally objects. What do you mean
לכתחילה *lechatchila* you can disproportionately be פודה הקדש hekdesh *podeh hekdesh*? Number
two is that even the more lenient opinion as it were by
the case of the $1,000 cow and the $800 cow said מדרבנן
*mi'derabanan* you had to pay the remaining 200. So what do you
mean לכתחילה *lechatchila* it's okay? So תוספות *Tosafos* reframes the word לכתחילה
*lechatchila* to not mean לכתחילה *lechatchila* like whether you're... but to mean
what are you consciously trying to do? When you are consciously trying,
you... you know you're doing, it's a little ironic, but you know
you're doing the wrong thing. You know you're taking a $1,000 thing
and transferring it to a penny. So you're like willfully, you know,
transferring it to lesser value. Then everybody agrees בדיעבד *be'di'eved* it works.
But when I said this cow in exchange for that cow, I
was trying to give הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* an equivalent value. So if
I was trying to give הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* an equivalent value, then
you could say then it doesn't work or finish working until I
genuinely do give הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh* equivalent value, okay, because that's what
I was trying to do. So that's how we frame the transfer.
It gives another way of thinking about it. I started before by
saying you could think about it two ways: you could think about
הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh* as an owner, as a property owner and then
for... like a sale and a מקח וממכר *mekach u'memkar*, or you
could think about it as a status and I transfer the status.
If I am take a $1,000 thing and try to be פודה
*podeh* it on a penny, I'm not buying it for a penny.
Clearly. Well, clearly what I'm doing is פדיון Pidyon, and I'm transferring
the קדושה. Kedushah. And that's why it works because I'm fully aware
of what I'm doing and I'm fully aware that it's disproportionate. And
therefore it works because it's really not a מקח. But when I
take a thousand dollar cow and I exchange it for an eight
hundred and I think that they're the same, I'm not just trying
to transfer קדושה, Kedushah, I think I'm actually doing a legitimate equivalent
exchange with הקדש. hekdesh And if I'm framing what I'm doing as
an exchange and not as a פדיון, Pidyon, it's more of I'm
exchanging it as a type of a מקח, then I have to
pay the full amount. Okay, so that's a nice way of saying
it. If you were trying to do a פדיון, Pidyon I would
agree with you, you can do a thousand dollars on a penny.
But if what you're trying to do is a מקח, is an
exchange or a purchase with הקדש, hekdesh. that's where רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan could say ביטול מקח יש להם. Then the exchange doesn't take
effect unless you're actually giving the paying the right amount of money.
All right, you got it? You're making a face. No?
I just don't understand how that helps the לכתחילה aspect why the
סיפא seifa you can do that.
No, you're not לכתחילה doing
it. לכתחילה does not mean you're allowed to do it לכתחילה the
way תוספות reads it. לכתחילה means that you are
trying to do it the right way, an equivalent exchange, then it
doesn't work. When does it work according to שמואל? When you're consciously
doing it disproportionate. Well, I mean it's like a חוטא ונשכר? choteh
v'niskar? Yeah, so we're not saying that it's allowed, meaning what תוספות
says is even according to שמואל you weren't allowed to do it.
Okay, nobody is saying you're allowed to, but if you know what
you're doing, even though you're not allowed or supposed to be doing
it, then it works because and I think that the way to
understand it is exactly the point we made. If you're trying to
do a פדיון, Pidyon, a פדיון focuses on the status of קדושה,
Kedushah, it could be disproportionate. It's not, you shouldn't be doing this
because you're cheating הקדש hekdesh out of the money because you're doing
an end run by doing it as a קדושה Kedushah not as
an exchange, but if that's what you're doing, you're doing a פדיון,
then it works. It's just a formal transfer of קדושה Kedushah and
it could be disproportionate. But if what you're trying to do is
a purchase or an equivalent exchange, then we could talk about ביטול
מקח יש להם. And then we could say, ah, if you hold
ביטול מקח then it's you don't finish being פודה it until you
give the right and the equivalent amount. And that's the position of,
at least according to this version, רבי יוחנן.
Rebbi Yochanan, Yes. This in-between between the מכירה mechira and the הקדשה
hakdasha solves all these problems. Except for,
like, theologically, the ערך erech is the glue that enables you to
understand that you're מקדיש makdish something. You know what I mean? Like,
it's the value,
קדושה Kedushah is too abstract. So I need to have some way
of thinking about קדושה. Kedushah. So I translate it into the
ערך erech as it were.
So that blurs it again.
You know what I mean? Well, I wouldn't say it's too abstract,
but I would say yes, you have both things. Meaning, it's not
abstract, you can think about your תפילין tefillin having קדושה Kedushah and
you don't think about it in terms of the money.
Right, yes you do. If they purchase a six hundred dollar thing.
Doesn't mean they don't put a, don't know what the cost is,
but that's not how you think about the קדושה Kedushah of your
תפילין. tefillin.
I'm not sure. In other words, the more expensive it is, the
more holy it is. Like there's that idea.
I don't know. I don't see, anyway, but yes, but
you have both of those ideas. Wouldn't you more likely throw a
pair of תפילין tefillin on the ground that cost twenty dollars versus?
There you go, sign the agenda. Right. So there are, yeah. All
right. I mean, maybe it depends how much you know, how much
of a whatever, capitalist you are. You know, like they say, like
the cynic, I keep forgetting that line, the cynic knows the cost
of everything, right, the cost of everything and the value of nothing,
right? So anyway, all right, so there's both of those ideas. That's
what makes הקדש hekdesh interesting. It has קדושה Kedushah and it's owned
by the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay, so which way do you
think about it? All right, so now the גמרא says like this:
איבעית אימא, Iba'it eima, if you want, לעולם בכדי הונאה. le'olam bichdi
hona'ah. We could say this debate of רבי יוחנן and ריש לקיש
of when the cows are worth different is when actually it's only
a very small difference, it's not the ביטול מקח range of difference.
So if it's only a small difference, why does ריש לקיש say
that even מן התורה min HaTorah you have to pay the difference?
Whatever happened to הקדש אין לו אונאה? Hekdesh ein lo hona'ah? So
the גמרא says: ולאו תהפוך ודרב חסדא קמיפלגי. v'lav tahapoch v'diRav Chisda
kamipalgi. Then what do they, so then you don't have to reverse
it because we're not talking about a ביטול מקח issue. So what
do they argue about and whatever happened to הקדש אין לו אונאה?
Hekdesh ein lo hona'ah? They argue about רב חסדא. Rav Chisda דאמר
מה אין להם אונאה De'amar ma ein lahem hona'ah because רב חסדא
reinterprets the אין לו אונאה ein lo hona'ah by הקדש. hekdesh, Too
bad Michael isn't here, he's very offended by this idea that you
could cheat הקדש, hekdesh that הקדש hekdesh, would ever lose out in
the transaction. So he says אין להם אונאה ein lahem hona'ah by
הקדש hekdesh means the following: אינם בתורת אונאה. einam b'torat hona'ah.
The laws of אונאה ona'ah don't apply לחומרא, l'chumra, meaning דאפילו פחות
מכדי אונאה חוזר. de'afillu pachot michdi hona'ah chozer.
When you're dealing business with הקדש, hekdesh even if you overcharged them
a penny, you have to give back the difference. Okay, so therefore
I guess if they overcharged you, they get away with it, but
if you overcharged... Following, in בתורת אונאה, b'torat ona'ah, the laws of
אונאה don't apply לחומרא, l'chumra, meaning דאפילו פחות מכדי אונאה חוזר. d'afillu
pachot mikdei ona'ah chozer. When you're dealing business with הקדש, hekdesh even
if you overcharge them a penny, you have to give back the
difference. Okay, so therefore, I guess if they overcharged you, they get
away with it, but if you overcharged them, you have to give
them back a penny. הקדש hekdesh? always wins. It's like Las Vegas,
the house always wins, right? הקדש hekdesh always wins. So therefore, that's
what their issue is. So they're so yes, קרקע, שטרות, shtarot עבדים,
that means you can overcharge and get away with it. All right,
but הקדש hekdesh... it means the opposite. It means that the restrictions,
it's sort of like, you know, the הלכה halacha that if, you
know, when we say an ox gores another ox, right, so it
doesn't apply, you know, to הקדש? hekdesh So rather than saying that
that means that, you know, הקדש hekdesh. you're exempt if you gore
the ox of הקדש, hekdesh, what it means is that you don't
pay half, you pay full. Right? So we interpret what the exclusion
means for הקדש to favor הקדש. So therefore, in the הקדש category,
being excluded from אונאה means you always pay the difference. And that's
at least what רבי יוחנן, what ריש לקיש said. So even if
it's only a tiny bit of a difference between cow one and
cow two, and it's even under the אונאה amount, it's only a
dollar difference, because it's הקדש, you have to pay that difference.
You said in בבא קמא Bava Kamma that you pay the full
amount if an ox gores הקדש? Yeah. Yep.
So what- yeah,
I think we said שור של הקדש? shor shel hekdesh? No,
don't- didn't we? I'm trying to remember. We certainly said that by
the case of the כנעני Kna'ani and the ישראל. Yisrael. Okay, anyway,
I have to go ahead and check. Okay, yeah.
Is
it how to understand the משנה mishna
when it says
הקדש in the משנה mishna. or is it-? Yes, it's how to
understand, right. Right. So yes, that is correct. That is correct. As
Eli points out, right, it's a very hard read of the משנה.
mishna The משנה mishna, lists all these things that אין להם אונאה,
ein lahem ona'ah, but it means something radically different by הקדש than
the other things. It's clearly not פשט of the משנה, mishna? but
it's motivated from a desire to protect הקדש's interest. Okay, I actually
have to check this thing about the שור. shor. I think it's
a- I think I got it right. Anyway, says like this: מיתיבי.
meitivei. I'm not sure about the שור. shor. מיתיבי: meitivei: ריבית ואונאה
להדיוט ואין ריבית ואונאה להקדש. ribbit v'ona'ah l'hedyot v'ein ribbit v'ona'ah l'hekdesh.
We have a ברייתא braita that says ריבית ribbit
and אונאה applies to a commoner, but it does not apply to
הקדש. Okay, so presumably that means that if you overcharge, you don't
have to pay it back. So the גמרא says, why does that
mean it any more than our משנה? mishna. מי אלימא ממשנתינו? mi
alima mimatnitin?
It's not any of a stronger statement than our משנה. mishna דאוקימנא
בתורת אונאה? d'okimna b'torat ona'ah?
So we reinterpreted in our משנה mishna, in a way that it
clearly didn't mean, to mean that the laws of- not that you
can overcharge, but it doesn't have the- the limits of אונאה. You
know, even smaller amounts you have to give back. הכא נמי, hacha
nami, we'll say the same thing. ריבית ודין אונאה להדיוט ואין ריבית
ודין אונאה להקדש. ribbit v'din ona'ah l'hedyot v'ein ribbit v'din ona'ah l'hekdesh.
We mean the same thing. By a normal, by a commoner, it's
not overcharging until it's a sixth; by הקדש, it's overcharging even a
little bit. So the גמרא says, one minute, that doesn't work with
the end of the
ברייתא. braita. This is a ברייתא. braita. אי הכי היינו דקתני סיפא?
ei hachi hainu d'katani seifa? וזה חומר בהדיוט מבהקדש. v'zeh chomer b'hedyot
mi'b'hekdesh. So this way, normally הקדש is stricter, but here the commoner
is stricter, because these laws apply to the commoner and not to
הקדש. But the גמרא says, but according to what you just said,
הקדש is stricter, because the laws apply to הקדש in even a
stricter fashion by אונאה. So the גמרא says, אריבית. a'ribbit. Okay, we
mean that in the ריבית ribbit case, it's stricter by a commoner
than by הקדש, but in the אונאה case, it's the reverse. The
גמרא says, ליתני נמי זה חומר בהקדש מבהדיוט אונאה. litni nami zeh
chomer b'hekdesh mi'b'hedyot ona'ah. So if that's true, then the ברייתא braita
should say, 'Well, when it comes to ריבית, ribbit, the commoner is
stricter; when it comes to אונאה, הקדש is stricter.' So the גמרא
says, הכי השתא? hachi hashta? What type of a question is that?
בשלמא זה חומר בהדיוט מבהקדש וסלו? bishlama zeh chomer b'hedyot mi'b'hekdesh v'sulo?
Because this is like the one
rare example where the law by a commoner is stricter than the
law by הקדש, right? אלא הקדש זה חומר וסלו? ela hekdesh zeh
chomer v'sulo? But to tell you by אונאה, 'Oh, look, by אונאה
הקדש is stricter,' like, okay, הקדש is stricter, like, of course, הקדש
is always stricter. Okay. So the גמרא says, so therefore since that
would be a silly thing to- like, no need to say it,
we're not pointing it out. But again, it's a radical reread of
the משנה, it's a radical reread of the ברייתא. braita. It sounds
like אונאה doesn't apply at all, and what we're really saying is
that the laws of אונאה are stricter. Okay.
And this is because we can imagine that the גזבר gizbar would
be involved in any type of ריבית ribbit transaction?
We wouldn't imagine it; it's the same type of exclusion. איש את
אחיו. ish et achiv. It's just excluded in the פסוק. Okay, so
now the גמרא is going to ask, what's the scenario? Let's take
a look. So ריבית דהקדש היכי דמי? ribbit d'hekdesh heichi dami? What
would be a case of ריבית ribbit not applying to הקדש? אילימא
דאוזיף גזבר מאה במאה ועשרין? eileima d'ozif gizbar me'ah b'me'ah v'esrin?
If the גזבר gizbar lent you a hundred dollars from הקדש funds,
you know, the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash could have a great side
business. The same way in Christian Europe, they used the Jews to
be their moneylenders, so now, you know, in Israel they could use
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash to be the bank and to be
the moneylenders because ריבית ribbit doesn't apply to the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. So the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is lending out all the
money on interest, okay? It's like, you know, Jesus kicked the moneylenders
out of the temple.
No, that wasn't the moneylenders, that was the moneychangers. That was the
moneychangers.
Okay, anyway, that's just a- okay.
By the way, I do want to say that if
הקדש...
I don't
know,
who are they borrowing money from who's charging them interest?
I don't know, the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* needs to borrow money
to do some capital, you know, some expansions and some... yeah, a
Jew. So if it only applies to איש את אחיו *ish es
achiv*, so would it apply when one of the sides is not
a אח *ach*, when one of the sides is, you know, or
is a בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*? So can they lend a Jew
with interest and can they borrow from a Jew with interest? That
would be the question, with interest, that would be the question.
In other words, can they borrow
and lend it from the גבוה *Gavoah* as opposed to אחיו *achiv*?
Exactly. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: Okay, לא תשיך לאחיך
*lo sashich leachicha*, that's the פסוק *pasuk*. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara*
says like this: היכי דמי *heichi dami*? אילימא דאוזיף דאוזפי גזבר מאה
במאה ועשרין *eileima d'ozif d'ozfei gizbar mei-ah b'mei-ah v'esrim*, the גזבר *gizbar*
lent out a hundred dollars and you pay him back a hundred
and twenty, לאו מעל גזבר *lav ma'al gizbar*? One minute, but then
the גזבר *gizbar* would be doing מעילה *meilah*. You're not the money
in the הקדש *hekdesh*'s treasury has קדושה *kedusha*, like we said. And
you're not allowed to lend it out. Like if you use, what
do you use that money for? You use that money to buy,
let's say, you know, stones or bricks or beams or whatever you're
going to buy, and then the קדושה *kedusha* transfers to the object
that you buy. Okay. Now there's actually an interesting question of how
does the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, how can it hire workers? What
happens to the קדושה *kedusha* when it uses the money to pay
the workers? So there normally what happens is that they pay the
workers after the work is done. So conceptually, you know, you went
ahead and you I don't know, polished off the stones in the
בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* and you've improved their value by polishing. And
now I go ahead and I pay you a hundred dollars for
your work, the קדושה *kedusha* of that money transfers to somehow the
increased value of the stones. That's conceptually what happens. Okay, funny thing
is let's say it doesn't what you did doesn't translate into increased
value. Let's say you came and you swept the בית המקדש *Beis
Hamikdash*, who knows. Okay, but anyway. But normally whenever הקדש *hekdesh* spends
their money, there has to be something that that קדושה *kedusha* transfers
to. Now if the גזבר *gizbar* is lending you money, what happened
to the קדושה *kedusha*? Right? Therefore there's nothing the קדושה *kedusha* transfers
to in that transaction, so it's just an act of מעילה *meilah*.
It's taking הקדש *hekdesh*'s money and putting it out of הקדש *hekdesh*.
So therefore if it's an act of מעילה *meilah*, besides that it's
not allowed, it would then fall back into the laws of, it
would logically the גמרא *Gemara* assumes fall back into the laws of
what do you call it, of ריבית *ribbis*, because then the money
stops being הקדש *hekdesh* money. Okay. So you don't have that scenario.
Now it's funny
that
the גמרא *Gemara* could have imagined the opposite scenario, which is what
I said, הקדש *hekdesh* borrows money. So there's no מעילה *meilah* issue,
they borrow money and now they have to pay back more. But
maybe the גמרא *Gemara* didn't want to imagine, a, two things: a,
didn't want to imagine that הקדש *hekdesh* needed to borrow money. You
know, I mean, kings in Europe needed to borrow money from the
Jews, that's actually part of that whole story, but anyway. But number
two is that maybe the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't want to assume that
הקדש *hekdesh* could be on the losing side of the transaction, like
the earlier discussion. ריבית *ribbis* doesn't apply even in that הוה אמינא
*hava amina* right? It could be that הקדש *hekdesh* can charge ריבית
*ribbis*. Maybe the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't want to imagine הקדש *hekdesh* paying
ריבית *ribbis*. So it says what's going to be the scenario that
הקדש *hekdesh* could charge ריבית *ribbis*? If the גזבר *gizbar* lends out
the money, then it's מעילה *meilah*, it loses its קדושה *kedusha* and
that ends the story there. Okay. וכיון דמעל גזבר יצאו מעותיו לחולין
*v'keivan d'maal gizbar yatziu maosav l'chulin*, דהוי ליה הדיוט *d'havei lei hedyot*,
so it's money of הדיוט *hedyot*. Now of course the interesting thing
you could say is, is that maybe the money doesn't have קדושה
*kedusha* but it's still owned by the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. Right?
What would be the story there? Would there be
ריבית *ribbis* by
property or אונאה *ona'ah*, any of these הלכות *halachos*, by property owned
by the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* that's in some
quirk didn't have קדושה *kedusha*? That gets to our question: is it
about the status or is it about the ownership? But at this
stage the גמרא *Gemara*'s assuming is that as soon as the money
is lent out, maybe two things happens, it loses its קדושה *kedusha*
and it's taken possession of by the other side. If I'm the
גזבר *gizbar* and I'm lending you a hundred dollars and you take
it, at that moment of taking it, it stops being הקדש *hekdesh*
and it stops being owned by הקדש *hekdesh* and it stops having
קדושה *kedusha* because you took it. So therefore ריבית *ribbis* now would
it would go to the normal laws. Okay, so let's see where
the גמרא *Gemara* continues. אלא *Ella*, so the גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר
רב הושעיא הכא במאי עסקינן *amar Rav Oshaya hacha bimai askinan*, what
are we talking about? כגון שקיבל עליו לספק סלתות מארבע ועמדו משלוש
*kegon shekibel alav lesapek s'lot mei'arba v'amdu meishalosh*. So this is going
to get us to the type of issues that are coming up
in the next פרק *perek*, so I won't get into the details
about this, but basically
הקדש *hekdesh* pays you, you're a supplier of a flour and it
needs it for the מנחות *menachos*, and they pay you when flour
is going at a four סאה *se'ah* per dollar, at four units
per dollar. And so they pay you a thousand dollars to provide
over the course of the year four thousand units of flour. But
then when it comes time to actually give the flour, now it's
going at three units per dollar. So if you're going to at
the end of the day give four thousand units for the thousand
dollars you got, even at the time when it's going at three
per dollar, הקדש *hekdesh* is getting back more than they gave, all
right? So ועמדו משלוש *v'amdu meishalosh*, מספק מארבע *mesapek mei'arba*, sorry, ועמדו
משלוש *v'amdu meishalosh*. כדתניא *kidtanya*, as it says in a ברייתא *braisa*,
המקבל עליו לספק סלתות מארבע ועמדו משלוש *hamakabel alav lesapek s'lot mei'arba
v'amdu meishalosh*. You agreed to pay at the four units per dollar
and now they're going at three, or מספק מארבע *mesapek mei'arba*, you
still have to pay at four even though now הקדש *hekdesh* is
getting four thousand units, although their money should have only bought them
three thousand units at today's prices. משלוש ועמדו מארבע *mishalosh v'amdu mei'arba*,
if you agreed that it was
the rate was three for dollar when you got your thousand dollars
and now they're going four per dollar, guess how much you have
to give הקדש *hekdesh*? מספק מארבע *mesapek mei'arba*. You always have to
give, הקדש *hekdesh* always gets the better of the two rates, okay?
שיד הקדש על העליונה *sheyad hekdesh al ha'elyona*. הקדש *hekdesh* always, the
house always wins, הקדש *hekdesh* always gets the better of the rate.
But in the case where they paid a thousand and it was
worth four at that time, and now when it's now it's worth
three and you're giving them four thousand, you're now giving them something
worth more than their thousand dollars, and even so that's acceptable because
it's הקדש *hekdesh*. רב פפא אמר *Rav Pappa amar*, now רב פפא
*Rav Pappa* says very interesting in terms of the whole conceptual framework
we've been constructing, רב פפא אמר הכא באבני בנין המסורות לגזבר עסקינן
*Rav Pappa amar hacha be'avnei binyan ham'suros legizbar askinan*. What we're dealing
about is הקדש *hekdesh* is lending out some raw material that they
have, they have these big stones that they're going to put in
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. But the stones aren't הקדש *hekdesh* yet,
and this is exactly the issue I was discussing. You can have
something owned by הקדש *hekdesh* because it has a property owner, which
does not have קדושה *kedusha*. And therefore when they can lend out
the stones, although I don't know why it's called lending because it's
not like you're giving back something different, but anyway that we'll discuss
that in the next פרק *perek*. They can lend out the stones
and get back more stones. I'm going to give you five of
these non-הקדש *hekdesh* stones that are in הקדש *hekdesh*'s quarry but they
don't have קדושה *kedusha*, they're owned by הקדש *hekdesh*, and you're going
to give back six, okay? So that would be allowed that would
not be because ריבית *ribis* doesn't apply to הקדש *hekdesh*. Why is
it not מעילה *me'ilah*? Because הקדש *hekdesh* owns those stones without making
them קדוש *kadosh* right away. כשמואל *keshmuel*, like שמואל *Shmuel* says, דאמר
שמואל בונין בחול ואחר כך מקדישין *de'amar Shmuel bonin bechol v'achar kach
makdishin*. First you build the stones into the building and then you're
מקדיש *makdish* the stones. You don't start with being מקדיש *makdish* and
one of the reasons is you got a big stone sitting around
in the quarry, what's the likelihood that somebody isn't going to be
leaning on it for a second? So if it was קדוש *kadosh*
to begin with, people would be being עובר מעילה *over me'ilah* left
and right. So the way they deal with it is they wait,
if I donate a stone to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, they
tell people don't be מקדיש *makdish* it. Give your stone to the
בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, after we get it built in the building,
then you can be מקדיש *makdish* it. So there's a way that
הקדש *hekdesh* can own something without it being קדוש *kadosh*. That's very
nice, it separates status and ownership. So that's a scenario where they
can lend out money, get back more in interest without there being
an issue of מעילה *me'ilah*, all right? So very nice in terms
of thinking about those two aspects of הקדש *hekdesh*. Yes?
Question. How as usual, these words, it has קדושה *kedusha*, it loses
its קדושה *kedusha*. Right. How how are you thinking about it out
in the, it's קדוש *kadosh*? Are you thinking about that it is
like a status, meaning it's like something that's off, like a name,
like you're naming it? Or it's something imminent, intrinsic, inside, embedded part
of it?
I mean, if you're asking me the image in my head, I
think we tend to think of it more as some type of
like a thing that fills it, some type of a thing inside
of it.
Essence or something.
Then you transfer that to something else, sure. All right, let's take
a look, the next גמרא *Gemara* goes very quickly. So okay, אין
בין תשלומי כפל kefel? *ein bein tashlumei kefel*. All these things, קרקע
*karka*, עבדים *avadim*, etc. there's no כפל kefel. *kefel*, the same way
there's no אונאה *ona'ah*. מנא הני מילי Mina hanei mili? *mana hanei
mili*? How you know this? דתנו רבנן Detanu rabbanan, *detanu rabanan*, על
כל דבר פשע *al kol devar pesha*, אשר יאמר כי הוא זה
עד האלהים יבא דבר שניהם אשר ירשיעון אלהים ישלם שנים לרעהו *asher
yomar ki hu zeh ad ha'elohim yavo devar sheneihem asher yarshi'un elohim
yeshaleim shenayim l'rei'ehu*. So the end of the פסוק *pasuk* is you
pay כפל kefel, *kefel*. על כל דבר פשע *al kol devar pesha*,
כלל klal, *klal*, that's a general. על השור על החמור על השה
על השלמה *al hashor al hachamor al haseh al hasalma*, פרט prat,
*prat*, that's specific. על כל אבידה *al kol aveida*, any lost thing,
אשר יאמר *asher yomar*, חזר וכלל chazar ve-khlal. *chazar vechlal*. That's a
general. כלל ופרט וכלל, אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. Klal u-prat
u-khlal iy atta dan ela k’ein haprat. It has to be like
the concrete. You know, anything generally like the concrete. בפרט מפורש דבר
המיטלטל וגופו ממון, Ba’prat meforash davar hamitaltel v’gufo mamon, chattel that has
intrinsic
value, אף כל דבר המיטלטל וגופו ממון, af kol davar hamitaltel v’gufo
mamon, same by anything. יצאו קרקעות, Yatzu karka-ot, it would exclude
land, שאינו מיטלטלין, she’eino mitaltelin, it's not chattel, it's not movable. יצאו
עבדים שהוקשו לקרקעות, Yatzu avadim she-hukshu l’karka-ot, slaves goes together with land.
יצאו שטרות שאף על פי שמיטלטלין, Yatzu shtarot she-af al pi she-mitaltelin,
documents of a debt or whatever, even though they're movables, אין גופן
ממון, ein gufan mamon, they do not have intrinsic value. הקדשות, now,
but why's הקדש excluded from כפל? kefel, אמר קרא רעהו, רעהו ולא
הקדש, Amar kra rei’ehu, rei’ehu v’lo hekdesh, your fellow, not הקדש. So
that's כפל. kefel, ולא תשלומי ארבעה וחמשה, V’lo tashlumei arba-ah v’chamishah, you
don't pay four and five. מאי טעמא? Mai ta’ama? That would only
apply by הקדש, the other things wouldn't be relevant because they're not
sheep and cow. מאי טעמא? Mai ta’ama? תשלומי ארבעה וחמשה אמר רחמנא
ולא תשלומי שלשה וארבעה. Tashlumei arba-ah v’chamishah amar rachmana v’lo tashlumei shlosha
v’arba-ah. Once you exclude it from כפל, kefel, so then the four
and the five, part of the four and five is the כפל,
so when you remove the כפל, it goes down to three and
four, and there's no הלכה three and four. So if they're excluded
from כפל, they're excluded from four and five. One more, שומר חינם
אינו נשבע, shomer chinam eino nishba, there's no שבועה shvua by שומר
חינם. shomer chinam. מנא הני מילי? Mina hanei mili? דתנו רבנן, Detanu
rabbanan, we taught, כי יתן איש אל רעהו, ki yiten ish el
rei’ehu, כלל, klal, כסף או כלים, kesef o kelim,
פרט, prat,
so it's a general, specific, right? Then it says לשמור lishmor is
the גרסא girsa on the side, חזר וכלל. chazar ve-khlal. כלל ופרט
וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. Klal u-prat u-khlal iy atta
dan ela k’ein haprat. מה הפרט מפורש דבר המיטלטל וגופו ממון, Ma
haprat meforash davar hamitaltel v’gufo mamon, so the same way כסף או
כלים kesef o kelim is movable and intrinsic value, אף כל דבר
המיטלטל וגופו ממון. af kol davar hamitaltel v’gufo mamon. יצאו קרקעות, Yatzu
karka-ot, excludes land, שאינו מיטלטלין, she’eino mitaltelin, which is not movables. יצאו
עבדים
שהוקשו לקרקעות, Yatzu avadim she-hukshu l’karka-ot, slaves are linked. יצאו שטרות שאף
על פי שמיטלטלין אין גופן ממון, Yatzu shtarot she-af al pi she-mitaltelin
ein gufan mamon, documents are movables but they don't have intrinsic value.
הקדשות, אמר קרא רעהו, Hekdeshot amar kra rei’ehu, if you give to
your friend to watch, רעהו ולא של הקדש. rei’ehu v’lo shel hekdesh.
One more, שומר שכר אינו משלם, shomer sachar eino meshalem, there's also
no payment for שומר שכר. shomer sachar. מנא הני מילי? דתנו רבנן,
כי יתן איש אל רעהו, ki yiten ish el rei’ehu, כלל, general,
חמור או שור או שה, chamur o shor o seh, פרט, is
a donkey or a sheep as a specific, וכל בהמה לשמור, v’chol
beheimah lishmor, any animal, חזר וכלל. כלל ופרט וכלל אי אתה דן
אלא כעין הפרט. iy atta dan ela k’ein haprat. מה הפרט מפורש,
you didn't know we're going to get through this so quickly, דבר
המיטלטל וגופו ממון, that's right, movables and intrinsic, אף כל דבר המיטלטל
וגופו ממון. af kol davar hamitaltel v’gufo mamon. יצאו קרקעות שאינו מיטלטלין,
Yatzu karka-ot she-eino mitaltelin,
land is not movables. יצאו עבדים שהוקשו לקרקעות, Yatzu avadim she-hukshu l’karka-ot,
slaves are linked to land. יצאו שטרות שאף על פי שמיטלטלין אין
גופן ממון, Yatzu shtarot she-af al pi she-mitaltelin ein gufan mamon, שטרות
don't have intrinsic value. הקדשות אמר קרא רעהו, amar kra rei’ehu, רעהו
ולא של הקדש. rei’ehu v’lo shel hekdesh.
Now before we end, we have one more minute, I want to
read this תוספות שומר חינם Tosafot shomer chinam because it deals with
an issue I mentioned yesterday. תוספות says, נראה, nireh, it's just that
the שומר חינם shomer chinam doesn't take a שבועה. shvua. What if
a שומר חינם shomer chinam is negligent, does he pay? So תוספות
says, נראה דהוא הדין דאינו משלם דאפילו שומר שכר אם פשע נראה
דלא משלם, nireh de-hu ha-din de-eino meshalem de-afilu shomer sachar im pashah
nireh de-lo meshalem,
and he quotes the גמרא. Now that's a question. That is actually
debated. Some say that negligent, you pay for, because negligent, similar to
the question before about ביטול מקח, negligent might not just be a
special דין din of שומרים. shomrim. Once you take a duty of
care, even though you don't pay as a שומר, shomer, you don't
take a שבועה shvua as a שומר, shomer, but negligence with somebody
who has a duty of care might be considered like a מזיק.
mazzik. And then you might have to pay from the category of
מזיק, mazzik, not the category of שומרים. shomrim. So תוספות raises that
question. He's inclined to think you don't pay for negligence, but that
is not clear. Does a שומר שכר shomer sachar and a שומר
חינם shomer chinam even by these things would they be paying for
negligence? All it says is that they don't make a שבועה shvua
and they don't pay for גניבה ואבידה. gneivah va-aveidah. For negligence it
could be conceived of as a very different category. Why is תוספות
inclined...